O.K. Today's דף daf is נ"ד, nun daled, 54. We're working through
the category of people that are חייב סקילה, chayav skila, particularly in
a whole range of sexual sins.
And we're picking up at the bottom of נ"ג עמוד ב', nun
gimmel amud bet, the debate of Reb Yehuda and the Chachamim, whether
a man who has intercourse with his mother, is that liable just
for mother, or also for father's wife, assuming it's also father's wife?
So Reb Yehuda says, only for mother, not for father's wife. Presumably
he understands that the פסוק pasuk about father's wife is talking specifically
about a stepmother. So the Gemara says, what's it based on? So
it says, let's read that again.
It says like this.
טעמא מאי? Ta'ama mai? So I guess we'll re-pick up from there,
it's about seven lines before the line gets wide. טעמא מאי, Ta'ama
mai, what's the reason? Beginning of the line, נ"ג עמוד ב'. nun
gimmel amud bet. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, דאמר קרא, d'amar k'ra, אמך
היא. imcha hee. She is your mother. משום אמה אתה מחייבו, Mishum
ima ata mechayvo, ואי אתה מחייבו משום אשת אב. v'ee ata mechayvo
mishum eshet av. So a person who's a man's mother,
the transgression is only for the sake of being the mother. And
if she also happens to be the father's wife, that's not, that
is not the violation.
That's what, that's the explanation of Reb Yehuda. So now the Gemara
asks, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, ערבת אשת אביך לא תגלה ערבת אביך
היא. ervat eshet avicha lo tegaleh ervat avicha hee.
The nakedness of your father's wife, this is the verse that prohibits
father's wife, you should not reveal because she is your, it is
the nakedness of your father. So it has that same doubling, you
know, same way one פסוק pasuk says אמך היא, imcha hee,
this says ערבת אביך היא. ervat avicha hee. So if we're to
understand that the word 'hee' comes to say you're only liable for
this identity and for no other identities, so we've got a problem,
right? 'Cause one פסוק pasuk says אמך היא, imcha hee, and the
other פסוק pasuk says ערבת אביך היא. ervat avicha hee. So if
you have this woman here who is both,
right, mother
and father's wife,
which happens a lot, no kidding, O.K.
So this פסוק pasuk says you're only חייב chayav because of mother.
And this פסוק pasuk will say, somebody who's your father's wife, you're
only going to be חייב chayav because of father's wife. So what
are you חייב chayav for? Right? Are you חייב chayav only for
mother and not father's wife, only father's wife not mother? So it
sort of like winds up you're not חייב chayav for anything, O.K.,
or it's contradictory. So that's what the Gemara says. Let's take a
look. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, ערבת אשת אביך לא תגלה ערבת אביך
היא. ervat eshet avicha lo tegaleh ervat avicha hee. משום אשת אב
אתה מחייבו, Mishum eshet av ata mechayvo, you make the person liable
for the father's wife, ואי אתה מחייבו משום אמה, v'ee ata mechayvo
mishum ima, and not for the mother. אלא אמה שהיא אשת אביו,
Ela ima she'hee eshet aviv, so what do you do with a
case of a mother who's a father's wife? האי הכא ממעיט לה,
Hai hacha mema'it lah, if you look at the פסוק pasuk of
אמך, imcha, you're excluding her from the father's wife category. והאי הכא
ממעיט לה, V'hai hacha mema'it lah, if you look at the פסוק
pasuk about father's wife, you're excluding her from the mother category. So
like, you know, the פסוקים pesukim basically wind up contradicting one another.
השתא אמו אינה כו', Hashta imo enah ko zan, like Rashi says
the next couple lines are a little just superfluous, but anyway, השתא
אמו שאינה אשת אביו
מחייב, hashta imo she'enah eshet aviv mechayve, so somebody who's just the
mother and not a father's wife, you'll say he's חייב, chayav, right?
'Cause that's clearly a case of mother. אשת אביו שאינה אמו מחייב,
Eshet aviv she'enah imo mechayve, and just a father's wife and not
a mother, מחייב, mechayve, those are clear. So this woman who happens
to be both, אמו שהיא אשת אביו, imo she'hee eshet aviv, לא
מחייב כלל, lo mechayve klal, you're gonna say she's excluded? Right? Well
one פסוק pasuk says she's not חייב chayav for mother, the other
פסוק pasuk says she's not חייב chayav for father's wife, so what,
she's not חייב chayav for anything? So anyway, ותו, v'su, so obviously
you have to, you can't, if you read the 'hee', you come
up with a contradiction. ותו, v'su, לרבנן נמי הכתיב l'rabbanan nami hakhtiv
אמך היא, imcha hee, and anyway, אמך היא, imcha hee, the Rabbis
who argue with Reb Yehuda are gonna have to say אמך היא
imcha hee means something. That's just sort of opening the door to
say that there's other ways we can deal with the פסוקים. pesukim.
O.K. So ההוא, hahu, so now we're going to say, what are
you going to do? We're going to put aside for a moment
the question of where Reb Yehuda gets his position from, and say
what are the other options to explain אמך היא. imcha hee. So
ההוא מיבעי ליה hahu mibaya leh לכריש לקיש בריה דרב אידי, l'ch'Resh
Lakish b'reih d'Rav Idi, like Resh Lakish the son of Rav Idi.
So now what's Resh Lakish the son of Rav Idi? Resh Lakish
the son of Rav Idi, I now have to remind myself and
look at Rashi.
Oh, yes, to make חייב chayav even after the father dies. So
no, that's אשת אביך, eshet avicha, excuse me, that's not אמך היא.
imcha hee. אמך היא imcha hee is, let me just check Rashi.
Yes, the אמך היא imcha hee is to say that the case
of the mother who's not the father's wife gets the punishment of
סקילה, skila, 'cause that's not explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. So somehow
the
דרשה drasha of אמך היא imcha hee gets us to the idea
that the mother who's not the father's wife gets סקילה skila 'cause
the פסוק pasuk is only explicit that father's wife gets סקילה. skila.
O.K. We'll see later how we do that. But the point is
we have something to do with the פסוק pasuk אמך היא. imcha
hee. If היא hi teaches us something else, so it's not necessarily
coming to teach us this idea that you only are חייב Chayav
for the mother status, and anyway the היא's hi would contradict one
another. So this is not going to work. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא מבעי ליה לכדרב ששת בריה דרב אידי. Ela mibaei lei
lechidrav Sheshet brei deRav Idi. אלא Ela so therefore אמך היא Imcha
hi needs to tell you something else anyway and
and anyway the two היא's hi are contradictory, so how are you
going to get to explain רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda position? אלא אמר
רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר קרא ערבתה. Ela amar Rav Acha
brei deRav Ika amar kra Ervata. Okay, so now let's actually write
out the פסוקים Psukim because a lot of today's פסוקs Pasuk discussion
is going to be dealing with the two פסוקים Psukim by אשת
אב Eshet Av and the two פסוקים Psukim by,
excuse me, the yeah, the two פסוקים, Psukim, the פסוק Pasuk by
אשת אב Eshet Av by the prohibition and then the punishment, that
everybody knows that in אחרי מות Acharei Mot of the prohibitions of
the עריות, Arayos, in קדושים Kedoshim you have the punishments of the
עריות, Arayos, and then the two פסוקים Psukim about the mother. Okay,
so here are the פסוקים. Psukim. So
here let's just write out these פסוקים. Psukim.
So in אחרי מות Acharei Mot you have ערבת אביך וערבת אמך
לא תגלה. Ervat avicha ve-ervat imcha lo tegaleh.
Let's use a working
pen. ערבת אביך וערבת אמך לא תגלה. Ervat avicha ve-ervat imcha lo
tegaleh. אמך היא לא תגלה ערבתה.
Imcha hi lo tegaleh
ervata. That's by the mother. How about the father's wife? Next
פסוק: Pasuk:
ערבת אשת אביך
לא תגלה ערבת אביך היא.
Ervat eshet avicha lo tegaleh ervat avicha
hi. Okay, so we have the two היא's hi that we focused
on before, but we said if somebody who is both a mother
and a father's wife, if the היא's hi meant to exclude the
other category, they're contradictory.
So how are we going to say that, explain רב יהודה's Rav
Yehuda position that just because of the mother and not because of
the father's wife? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא אמר
רב אחא
בריה דרב איקא אמר קרא ערבתה. Ela amar Rav Acha brei deRav
Ika amar kra Ervata. Okay, לא תגלה ערבתה. lo tegaleh ervata. So
now we're not going to focus on the היא, hi, we're going
to focus on the ערבתה. Ervata. לא תגלה ערבתה משום ערוה אחת
אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום שתי עריות. lo tegaleh ervata mishum
ervah achat ata mechayvo ve-i ata mechayvo mishum shtei arayos. Okay, ערבתה,
Ervata, her ערוה, ervah, somehow the her means it's one identity, so
only because of the אמך imcha status and it's not going to
be another status, somebody who's a mother. אלא מעתה, Ela me-ata, so
the גמרא Gemara says no because then you're going to get into
problems with other פסוקים. Psukim. ערבת כלתך לא תגלה אשת בנך היא,
Ervat kalatcha lo tegaleh eshet bincha hi, לא תגלה ערבתה lo tegaleh
ervata by the daughter-in-law, הכא נמי משום ערוה אחת אתה מחייבו ואי
אתה מחייבו משום שתי עריות. hacha nami mishum ervah achat ata mechayvo
ve-i ata mechayvo mishum shtei arayos. So we should say daughter-in-law you
can't have a double identity, and the double identity would be she's
your son's wife and she's a married woman. Now, so maybe רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda would say that, maybe you wouldn't be liable for
married woman, only for son's wife. No, והתנן הבא על כלתו חייב
עליה משום כלתו ומשום אשת איש, ve-hatnan habah al kalato chayav aleiha
mishum kalato u-mishum eshet ish, the משנה Mishna says that a man
who has intercourse with his daughter-in-law transgresses daughter-in-law and married
woman בין בחיי בנו בין לאחר מיתת בנו, bein be-chayei beno bein
le-achar mitat beno, whether son's alive or dead, ולא פליג רב יהודה
עלה, ve-lo palig Rav Yehuda alah, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda only disagrees
with mother that it's one, that it's one identity. He doesn't disagree
with daughter-in-law. So ערבתה Ervata is going to tell you one identity,
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda should be disagreeing with the daughter-in-law case as
well. אלא כיון דחד גופא היא, Ela keivan de-chad gufa hi, what
must we say? Since it's one body, one person, אע"ג דתרי איסורי
נינהו, af al gav de-trei issurei ninhu, even though it's two statuses,
two identities, כתיב ערבתה. ktiv Ervata. The word ערבתה Ervata doesn't exclude
it. Okay, ערבתה, Ervata, you know it is ערבתה Ervata because it's,
you know, it's her identity, it doesn't exclude another identity. הכא נמי,
Hacha nami, that's what we would say by daughter-in-law, הכא נמי כיון
דחד גופא היא אע"ג דתרי איסורי נינהו כתיב ערבתה. hacha nami keivan
de-chad gufa hi af al gav de-trei issurei ninhu ktiv Ervata. Okay,
so ערבתה Ervata doesn't work, היא Hi doesn't work because then we
have the היא hi over here, ערבתה Ervata doesn't work because then
we have it by daughter-in-law. Okay, so none of these words work.
אלא אמר רבא קסבר רב יהודה ערבת אביך זו אשת אביך. Ela
amar Rava kasvar Rav Yehuda ervat avicha zu eshet avicha. So now
what we're going to deal with is the funny fact that we
have the word ערבת אביך Ervat Avicha here. What does it mean
father's nakedness? So there are three possibilities. It could mean to actually
have intercourse with the father. We'll get to that, we'll get to
that possibility, it doesn't. Well there's the ו Vav וערבת אמך. ve-ervat
imcha.
Right,
so the and then the explanation that
says, you know, וערבת אמך, ve-ervat imcha, so the whole thing seems
to, right? So the other possibility is by, you know, having intercourse
with the mother that is an extension of the father's nakedness, that's
probably פשט pshat and here we have ערבת אביך Ervat Avicha by
the father's wife. Okay, so now אשת אביך ערבת אביך היא. eshet
avicha ervat avicha hi. And by the way, conceptually, if we're dealing
with a mother who's not the father's wife, it's not so obvious.
Why would we conceptualize that as the father's nakedness, right? A
man that this woman once had intercourse with for somebody for the
son to have intercourse with his mother is revealing the father's identity?
It makes more sense if it's currently the father's wife that we
conceptualize it as father's nakedness. So what do you do with ערבת
אביך? Ervat Avicha? So what we are going to say is is
that yes, especially looking at this פסוק, Pasuk, ערבת אביך Ervat Avicha
means אשת אביך. Eshet Avicha. Okay, which is a very reasonable explanation,
right? And that we're just assuming that the mother is אשת אביך.
Eshet Avicha. So let's look at how we're going to read this.
אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, תסבר רבי יהודה, Tasbar Rabbi Yehuda,
ערבת אביך זו אשת אביך, Ervat Avicha zo Eshet Avicha, ומסיק ליה
בגזרה שוה. Umasik lei bi'gezeirah shavah. Okay, you have גזרה שוה, Gezeirah
shavah, here ערבת אביך Ervat Avicha is אשת אביך, Eshet Avicha, here,
so that's what it means here. Very reasonable read of the
פסוקים. Pesukim. ומשמע בין אשת אביו שהיא אמו בין אשת אביו שאינה
אמו. U'mashma bein Eshet Aviv she'hee immo bein Eshet Aviv she'einah immo.
And that would include a father's wife, whether mother or not mother.
אמו שאינה אשת אביו מנלן? Immo she'einah Eshet Aviv minalan? The one
thing we have not included yet in this word ערבת אביך Ervat
Avicha is mother who's not father's wife. תלמוד לומר ערבת אמך לא
תגלה אמך היא. Talmud lomar Ervat imcha lo tegaleh imcha hee. So
that's the end of the פסוק, Pasuk, okay, father's wife, whether has
single or double identity, and now just mother, who's not the father.
משום אמו אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום אשת אביו. Mishum immo
ata mechayvo ve'ei ata mechayvo mishum Eshet Aviv. Now it seems like
we went back to what we sort of said before and we
said since it's saying אמך, Imcha, it means that it's only the
identity because of אמך. Imcha. So there's a very long רש"י Rashi
that basically tries to explain how we've now made things better, but
the basic point is is that what we what we have done,
I'm just going to simplify this. What we have done is we've
introduced up here somebody that's got a double
identity, Superman and Clark Kent. No, a mother who's a father's wife
is included in here. And then as you continue to read the
פסוק, Pasuk, and even somebody who's a mother and a father's wife
and somebody who's just a mother, אמך היא. Imcha hee. For for
one minute. For both of those women, whether she's a father's wife
or not a father's wife, the only relevant איסור Issur is אמך
היא. Imcha hee. And then what you're left with here is the
אשת אב Eshet Av who isn't the mother. Okay, so this initially
included both אשת אב Eshet Av that was the mother and wasn't
the mother. And then you continue, but of course the אשת אב
Eshet Av alone is going to be included down here. So effectively,
the point is that includes the אשת אב Eshet Av that is
the mother, and then the mother who's not the אשת אב. Eshet
Av. So whether it's an אשת אב Eshet Av who is a
mother or just a mother alone, the only liability is going to
be for mother. Okay, so it's not a bad read. What it
says is ערבת אביך Ervat Avicha is including the mother who's the
father's wife. And once it's including the mother who's the father's wife,
it's telling you the only transgression is for mother and not father's
wife.
Couldn't you just said ערבת אשת אביך? Ervat Eshet Avicha?
No,
by leaving it vague it allows this to be to be whatever,
to be, you know, in the end to be clarified as being
mother who's father's wife. So mother who's father's wife or just mother
the liability is only for mother. Okay, so that's in the end
how we do it.
And you said ערבת אמך לא תגלה,
Ervat imcha
lo tegaleh, that's it.
What? Couldn't you have just said then...
no, because then I would have said that a mother who's somebody
who's a mother and a father's wife you're liable for both. But
by putting this up here and saying father's wife up here and
saying but the only liability is for mother, the only transgression is
for mother, that's how Rava... that's how it's Rava. Okay, so whatever
we'll worry about the רבנן, Rabbanan, we'll see about the רבנן Rabbanan
in a minute. But by the way, you know sometimes you do
these crazy דרשות Drashot and you say okay fine, whatever. But here,
but but here it's not a bad read. ערבת אביך Ervat Avicha
does seem to be referring, why is intercourse with the mother a
violation of ערבת אביך? Ervat Avicha? Presumably because we're talking about a
mother who's a father's wife. And then what it's telling you is
a mother who's a father's wife, the only liability is for mother.
Okay, so that's how he reads it. Or
something like that, although אמך, Imcha, אמך Imcha also includes mother who's
not father's wife. So okay. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרבא. Tanya kavatei de'Rava.
We taught like Rava.
That's going to use the פסוק Pasuk this way to explain רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's position and then we'll also see what it does
with the רבנן's Rabbanan's position. Okay, איש אשר ישכב את אשת אביו.
Ish asher yishkav et Eshet Aviv. Okay,
so now we're going to look at the פסוקים Pesukim now, what
we have to do is we have to worry about the פסוקים
Pesukim by the the punishment and not just by the what do
you call it, not just by the prohibition. So now we're in
קדושים. Kedoshim. Okay, so hold on.
ואיש אשר ישכב את אשת אביו.
Ve'ish asher
yishkav
et Eshet Aviv.
Hold on, let me find it. ואיש Veish, אשר ישכב asher yishkav,
את אשת... wait, actually אשת אביו eshet aviv, should be
down here,
excuse me. ואיש אשר ישכב את
אשת אביו.
Ve'ish asher yishkav et
Eshet Aviv. Where were we? ערבת אביו גילה. Ervat Aviv gillah. ערבת
אביו
גילה.
Ervat Aviv gillah.
מות
יומתו דמיהם בם. Mot yumatu dmeihem bam.
So
by the way, this of course tells me סקילה, Sekilah, right? Okay.
מות יומתו דמיהם בם. Mot yumatu dmeihem bam. שניהם, Shneihem, thank you.
Okay,
דמיהם
בם. dmeihem bam. Now, guess what's not here?
You know what's not here? Mother. Okay, so, let's take a look.
All right, so now let's look at this ברייתא. Braisa. Okay. All
right. So, תניא כוותיה דרב, Tanya kevasei d'Rav, ואיש,
פרט לקטן. Prat lekatan.
Okay,
if a minor does it, the minor doesn't get punished, and if
he's minor enough, even the woman doesn't get punished, we'll deal with
that later, under the age of nine it's not considered an act
of intercourse, even the woman doesn't get punished. אשר ישכב את אשת
אביו. Asher yishkav et eshet aviv. Okay, משמע בין אשת אביו שהיא
אמו בין אשת אביו שאינה אמו. Mashma bein eshet aviv shehi imo
bein eshet aviv sheina imo.
So that would include whether mother or not mother. אמו שאינה אשת
אביו מניין? Imo sheina eshet aviv minayin?
How do I know to include a mother that's not the father's
wife? תלמוד לומר ערבת אביו גילה. Talmud lomar ervat aviv gila. So
this extra פסוק, pasuk, ערבת אביו גילה, ervat aviv gila, here, ironically,
especially given what we were just explaining, ironically comes to mean mother
who is not father's wife. This includes all father's wives. We've got
a problem though, mother is not mentioned anywhere in the punishment. So
we're going to stick mother in based on this extra thing. Okay,
so this thing, although again, it's funny that before ערבת אביך ervat
avicha was about father's wife, and here it's about mother. Okay, so
this is going to allow us to include just mother.
Okay.
And that's an acceptable way of a פסוק pasuk to kill somebody?
Well, what can I tell you, yes. I don't know what I'm
supposed to what I'm supposed to say, yes. I mean everything is
דרשות. drashot. I mean, okay.
מופנה. Mufne.
Now, מניין תלמוד לומר ערבת אביו גילה. minayin talmud lomar ervat aviv
gila. Now how do we know it? מופנה להקיש וללמוד ממנו גזירה
שוה. Mufne lehakesh v'lilmod mimenu gezeira shava. And we're going to use
this later to make a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. We're not going
to tell you now what the גזירה שוה gezeira shava is, we're
going to hold you in suspense. Okay, we'll get back to that.
מות יומתו, Mot yumatu, בסקילה. besekilah. אתה אומר בסקילה או אינו אלא
באחת מכל מיתות האמורות בתורה? Ata omer besekilah o eino ela b'achat
mikol mitot haamurot batorah?
How do you know it's סקילה? sekilah? נאמר כאן דמיהם בם ונאמר
באוב וידעוני דמיהם בם. Ne'emar kan dmeihem bam vene'emar b'ov veyidoni dmeihem
bam. So this is of course the אוב וידעוני ov veyidoni and
the דמיהם בם dmeihem bam and the way we get to סקילה
sekilah for most of the people in this category. מה להלן בסקילה
אף כאן בסקילה. Mah lehalan besekilah af kan besekilah. Fine. עונש שמענו,
Onesh shamanu, אזהרה מניין? azhara minayin? So now we've got the punishment
for father's wife and mother by sneaking her in. Okay. Where do
we know that it's prohibited? Because it's not enough for the punishment,
the principle is אין עונשין אלא אם כן מזהירין. Ein onshin ela
im ken mazhirin. You cannot the punishment requires a verse to actually
say that it's prohibited. So where is that verse? תלמוד לומר ערבת
אביך לא תגלה וערבת אמך. Talmud lomar ervat avicha lo tegale v'ervat
imcha. Okay, ערבת אביך, ervat avicha, זו אשת אביך. zo eshet avicha.
So now up here, that's אשת אביך, eshet avicha, ironically, even though
here it was your mother, here it's אשת אביך. eshet avicha. זו
אשת אביך. Zo eshet avicha. אתה אומר אשת אביך או אינו אלא
ערבת אביך ממש? Ata omer eshet avicha o eino ela ervat avicha
mamash? Maybe it means literally intercourse with the father. נאמר כאן ערבת
אביך לא תגלה ונאמר להלן ערבת אביו גילה. Ne'emar kan ervat avicha
lo tegale vene'emar lehalan ervat aviv gila. ערבת
אביו גילה, Ervat aviv gila, right here back here the other פסוק
pasuk we were looking at by the punishment. So this is ערבת
אביו גילה ervat aviv gila in the context of sleeping with a
woman. So ערבת אביך ervat avicha here clearly doesn't mean sleeping with
a father, it means sleeping with a woman that's considered the father's
nakedness. מה להלן באשה הכתוב מדבר אף כאן באשה הכתוב מדבר. Mah
lehalan b'isha hakatuv medaber af kan b'isha hakatuv medaber. So here too
ערבת אביך ervat avicha has to mean a woman who is defined
as the father's nakedness. ומשמע, Umashma, so בין אשת אביו שהיא אמו
בין אשת אביו שאינה אמו. bein eshet aviv shehi imo bein eshet
aviv sheina imo. And since it would be included אשת אביו, eshet
aviv how we know it's אשת אביו eshet aviv is not clear
since here it means mother, maybe it means אשת אביו eishet aviv?
because of down here. But this means father's wife regardless of mother
or not mother, this is just like רבא Rava said. אמו שאינה
אשת אביו מניין? Imo sheina eshet aviv minayin? How do I know
it's just mother? תלמוד לומר וערבת אמך לא תגלה. Talmud lomar v'ervat
imcha lo tegale. The continuation of the פסוק. pasuk. אם כן למה
נאמר באזהרה שעשה הכתוב אמו שאינה אשת אביו כאמו שהיא אשת אביו?
Im ken lama ne'emar b'azhara she'asa hakatuv imo sheina eshet aviv k'imo
shehi eshet aviv?
So here I know that the mother who is not the father's
wife is treated the same as the father's wife who is not
the mother, they're both included in this פסוק pasuk and they're both
equal, right? That's that דרשה. drasha. This is father's wife, this is
mother, they're equally included in the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, עונש מניין? onesh
minayin?
Now this is going to get back to telling us how do
we know that this is basically the mother and that this is
that they're both going to get סקילה. sekilah. נאמר כאן ערבת אביך
לא תגלה ונאמר להלן ערבת אביו גילה. Ne'emar kan ervat avicha lo
tegale vene'emar lehalan ervat aviv gila. Okay, מה באזהרה עשה הכתוב אמו
שאינה אשת אביו כאמו שהיא אשת אביו, mah b'azhara asa hakatuv imo
sheina eshet aviv k'imo shehi eshet aviv,
the same way it treated the mother whether she's married to the
father or not married to the father—this is mother married to the
father, this is mother not married—and both of them get the same
prohibition. אף בעונש עשה הכתוב אמו שאינה אשת אביו כאמו שהיא אשת
אביו. Af b'onesh asa hakatuv imo sheina eshet aviv k'imo shehi eshet
aviv. So here too don't think that this ערבת אביו גילה—this ervat
aviv gila is getting back to I think clarifying what it said
before—don't think this ערבת אביו גילה ervat aviv gila is limited to
mother who is also... also אשת אב eishet av *eshet av*. That
would have been a reasonable thing to think, right? Here ערות אביך
*Ervat avikha* and ערות אביך *Ervat avikha* we're saying means mother—means אשת
אב eishet av *eshet av*, right? And ערות אביך *Ervat avikha* anyway
conceptually we said means אשת אב eishet av *eshet av* more than
it means mother. So here, even if you wanted to tell me
ערות אביו גילה *Ervat aviv gillah* includes mother, maybe it just means
mother who is also אשת אב eishet av, *eshet av*, right? That
would be reasonable. The whole פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is אשת אב eishet
av *eshet av*, this phrase ערות אביך *Ervat avikha*, you know, would
be including אשת אב *eshet av*. So maybe it means mother who
is also אשת אב *eshet av*. How do I know it means
mother that's alone even if she's not אשת אב *eshet av*? Ah,
because I link it to here. And in this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
I have mother who's אשת אב *eshet av* and mother who's not
אשת אב *eshet av*. So here too, I have mother who's אשת
אב *eshet av* and mother who's not אשת אב *eshet av*. So
that's how—that was remember to מופנה לגזירה שווה *mufneh l'gezeirah shavah*, this
is the גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah*. Okay, so this gives you mother
and—or this gives you, you know, אשת אב *eshet av* and mother,
and this gives you אשת אב *eshet av*—the פשט *pshat* of the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* gives you אשת אב *eshet av* plus mother, that's
ערות אביך *Ervat avikha*, אשת אב *eshet av* plus mother, and then
the גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah* gives you just mother alone.
Okay, so now we've got everybody getting the punishment of סקילה skilah,
*skilah*. Okay, and we've got here, you know, you know, everybody getting
prohibited. Okay, so now it says like
this: אף עונש עשה הכתוב אמו שאינה אשת אביו eishet aviv כאמו
שהיא אשת אביו eishet aviv *Af onesh asa hakatuv immo she'einah eshet
aviv ke'immo shehi eshet aviv*.
Now we have yet to do with the point about how do
we know that for mother it's only the one identity, even if
she's both an אשת אב *eshet av*. אמך היא imcha hi, משום
אמו אתה מחייבו ואתה מחייבו משום אשת אב *Imkha hi mishum immo
atah m'khayeiv ve'atah m'khayeiv mishum eshet av*. Once this means mother, you
know, this, you know, wife who's also mother, and this means mother
and whether regardless the only liability is for mother, not also for
wife, and that's Rabbi Yehuda's position. Now how do we know this
is going—I mean obviously it's going through Rabbi Yehuda because the position
links up with Rabbi Yehuda. But Rashi also makes the point that
this is a דרשה *drasha* of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, it's in
תורת כהנים *Torat Kohanim* in the ספרא *Sifra*, the Tannaic work on
ויקרא *Vayikra*, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that the סתם ספרא
*stam Sifra*, the anonymous voice of the ספרא *Sifra*, is Rabbi Yehuda.
So actually it, you know, it works very nicely. This is Rabbi
Yehuda's דרשה *drasha*, this is how we know you're only liable for
the identity of mother. All right, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* turns to the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanon*. Okay,
what Michael wants to know. That was all how Rabbi Yehuda deals
with it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ורבנן V'Rabbanan,
ערות אביך ממש mamash? *Verabbanon, ervat avikha mamash*. Now the רבנן Rabbanan.
*Rabbanon* would say, if you read ערות אביך *Ervat avikha* to be
this thing of mother's wife—father's wife and mother, and then you're going
to end by saying you're only liable for mother, so the Rabbis
can't do that because they say that a father's wife and a
mother you get both statuses. So what do they do with ערות
אביך *Ervat avikha*? So ערות אביך *Ervat avikha* for them is intercourse
with the father. Okay, that is what it—ממש *mamash*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute: האי מאת זכר zachar, נשכב nishkav *Hai
m'ezkhar nishkav*? But that's the prohibition of a man having intercourse with
another man. לחייב עליו שתים *L'khayeiv alav shtayim*. That's to say that
you get two prohibitions. Okay. וכדרב יהודה *Ukhed'Rav Yehuda*. You say it's
true, it's a double status. אין הכי נמי *Ein hakhi nami*. A
lot of other people are double status. Father's wife who's a mother,
son's—son's wife, right? Married woman and a—and a daughter-in-law. So this too.
חייב שתים chayav shtayim, *Khayeiv shtayim*. אמך היא imcha hi *Imkha hi*.
It's only going on the second פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. ערות אביך *Ervat
avikha*, right. For the ערות אמך imcha. *Ervat imkha*, that's אמך היא
*Imkha hi*. ערות אביך *Ervat avikha* separately. Because here's ערות אביך *Ervat
avikha* here also, yeah I don't know. I don't know. Rabbi Yehuda's
דרש *drash* reading is a much nicer reading. וכדרב יהודה *Ukhed'Rav Yehuda*.
This is Rav Yehuda, not Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר רב יהודה נכרי הבא
על אביו חייב שתים Ha'ba al aviv chayav shtayim *De'amar Rav Yehuda:
Nokhri haba al aviv khayeiv shtayim*. If a non-Jew, okay, has intercourse
with his father he's liable twice. Now why it says non-Jew we'll
see in a minute. הבא על אחי אביו חייב שתים Ha'ba al
achi aviv chayav shtayim *Haba al akhi aviv khayeiv shtayim*. Or if
he has intercourse with his father's brother twice, because it's—because it's with
a man and with a—well we're going to say—we're actually talking about
a Jew, we just don't like describing these acts for—okay—חייב chayav שתים
*khayeiv shtayim*. So אמר רב *Amar Rav*—so anyway with his father's brother,
one because of a man and one because of the—the same way
ערות אביך *Ervat avikha* there's a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that talks about
ערות אחי אביך achi avicha *Ervat akhi avikha*. Your brother—your father's brother's
nakedness. So does that mean ממש *mamash* or does that mean your
father's brother's wife? So we're reading all these things as ממש *mamash*,
literally father, literally father's brother, and it'll be two transgressions. אמר רבא
Rava מסתברא מילתא דרב יהודה בישראל בשוגג ובקרבן be'Yisrael be'shogeg u'be'korban. *Amar
Rava: Mistabra milta d'Rav Yehuda b'Yisrael b'shogeg uvekurban*. He says we're not
really talking about a non-Jew. We're talking about a Jew. And we're
going to say non-Jew as a euphemism. But even if we're talking
about a Jew, why do I care that it's—that you have two
liabilities? You can't kill a person twice and both of them are
the same punishment. So one possibility would be what I said the
other day, which is that you warned him about one and not
the other. You say, wait, you know, you can't have intercourse with
she's your father's wife. And then he said, you know, and then
then according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, he'd get off because it
was
also his
mother.
So you have to warn him. Can you—is the warning considered legitimate
warning? You have to know if it's covered in this category or
not. But the גמרא Gemara says the more—the more issue the גמרא
Gemara focuses on is that if it was done בשוגג, be'shogeg, then
if it's different statuses and different transgressions, you'd bring a separate קרבן
korban for each one. So the real relevance of this teaching is
בישראל בשוגג be'shogeg ובקרבן. Okay, a Jew and it was done בשוגג
for the sake of a קרבן. korban. She would only
bring one קרבן. korban. She would only bring—that's an interesting
question. I mean, he also transgressed both prohibitions. I mean, it's true
it's framed in terms of the man, but no, that's
a good point. I think
she would bring two as well. Yeah, I think she would bring
two as well. והא דקאמר נכרי—so Ve'ha de'ka'amar nochri why do they
say a non-Jew? לשנא מעליא הוא—it's Lishna ma'alya hu a euphemism. די
סלקא דעתך נכרי ממש—now De'i salka daitach nochri mamash it can't mean
non-Jew. Now it is true that בני נח Bnei Noach does cover
non-Jews, and it covers them in terms of, you know, sex between
men is covered, and intercourse between men, and also—now, father, whether it's
whether with father or just mother or father's wife or whatever, anyway,
in theory we could be having this conversation. But he says no,
that's not possible, because דינו מאי ניהו—what dino mai nihu do you
do—what's the only judgment for a non-Jew? קטלא—it's Katala execution. There's no
קרבנות. korbanot. And even my interesting issue about how you warn him,
what, you know, there's no התראה, hatra'ah, there's no warning that's necessary
for the laws of בני נח. Bnei Noach. So therefore, all we
can talk about is execution. We can't talk about קרבנות, korbanot, so
who cares how many categories you put somebody in? בתרי קטלי קטלת
ליה—you're Be'trei katlei katlat lei gonna kill him twice? Okay, so therefore
we have to be talking about a Jew and for a קרבן.
korban. Now, I have to say here, and I'm gonna have to—and
this is of course gonna become an issue when we get to
the bottom of the דף. daf. And I just have to like—I
just have to like say this. You know, we're gonna be exploring
here—I mean, we've started, right, the issue of משכב זכור—like, mishkav zachor
you know, sex between two men. And obviously it's a very sensitive
issue—intercourse between two men, you know, because of—now, we just have very
different I think sensibilities nowadays, you know, around these issues and—and about
gay people and so on. And I—I really—I'm gonna just read the
גמרא Gemara and explain it. You know, I just have to acknowledge
that it presents a lot of—you know, and I can certainly only
imagine for a gay man who is learning this דף, daf, you
know, how hurtful or painful these things are. But—anyway, but now that
I've said that, I'm just gonna have to read it and I'm
just gonna read it and explain it in its own terms. All
right, we can talk more about it later, but let's go on.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. All right,
תניא נמי הכי—we Tanya nami hachi taught similarly. הבא על אביו חייב
שתים—a man who has intercourse with his father, two transgressions. הבא על
אחי אביו חייב שתים—his father's brother, same thing. איכא דאמרי Ika de'amri
some say דלא כרבי יהודה—that de'lo ke'Rebbe Yehuda goes against רבי יהודה,
Rebbe Yehuda meaning רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda interprets this to be about
a father's wife and therefore he would say that it's not talking
about—about intercourse with a father and that would not be a separate
prohibition, intercourse with a father. That's a reasonable conclusion. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika
de'amri another say אפילו תימא רבי יהודה afillu teima Rebbe Yehuda even
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, ומייתי לה בקל וחומר מאחי אביו u'mayti lah
be'kal v'chomer me'achi aviv he could actually learn out intercourse with the
father from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from intercourse with the father's
brother. ומה אחי אביו דקורבה דאביו הוא—so U'mah achi aviv de'kurva de'aviv
hu by the verse by the father's brother, okay, it actually—that everybody
agrees is literal. 'Cause what does it say there? It says—wait, what
does it say? ערוות אחי אביך לא תגלה אל אשתו לא תקרב
דודתך היא. Ervas achi avicha lo tegaleh el ishto lo tikrav dodascha
hi. So it starts with אחי אביך achi avicha and it ends
with דודתך. dodascha. And the punishment says—what does the punishment say? I
don't know. But anyway, we assume רש״י—let Rashi me just check רש״י,
Rashi, hold on. Okay, so somehow because right, since somehow the פסוק
pasuk is, you know, I don't know why it's so clear, but
since the פסוק pasuk speaks about both things, it says ערוות אחי
אביך לא תגלה אל אשתו לא תקרב דודתך היא. Ervas achi avicha
lo tegaleh el ishto lo tikrav dodascha hi. So we could have
assumed that part B is clarifying part A. What does אחי אביך
mean? It means אל אשתו לא תקרב. el ishto lo tikrav. But
somehow the גמרא gemara is assuming, no, everybody would agree that that
פסוק pasuk. is referring to two separate prohibitions—אחד אבות אחי אביך לא
תגלה echad avos achi avicha lo tegaleh and אל אשתו לא תקרב.
el ishto lo tikrav. So everybody is going to agree that by
the father's brother there is a prohibition of actually intercourse with the
father's brother himself. Okay, and therefore רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehudah, even though
he doesn't have the father included... he's gonna learn out the father
from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, מייתי לה בקל וחומר מאחי
אביו. ma'isi la b'kal vachomer me'achi aviv. ומה אחי אביו דקורבה דאביו
הוא, u'ma achi aviv d'kurba d'aviv hu, even a relative of the
father חייב שתים, you transgress twice with intercourse with the father's brother,
אביו לא כל שכן aviv lo kol shekein how much more so
with the father himself. Now normally we don't like קל וחומרין kal
vachomerin when we're talking about things like punishments and death penalties and
so on. So the גמרא says this question of whether ר' יהודה
Reb Yehuda would say intercourse with the father is a prohibition, can
you learn it from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, would ר' יהודה
Reb Yehuda say that? קמיפלגי בפלוגתא דאביי ורבא, kamiflagi b'plugta d'Abaye v'Rava,
it's the debate the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא which we
will see elsewhere. מר סבר עונשין מן הדין ומר סבר אין עונשין
מן הדין. mar savar onshin min hadin u'mar savar ein onshin min
hadin. Can you learn out a punishment based on a קל וחומר
kal vachomer or not based on a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Okay,
so that's the question, but basically the רבנן Rabbanan, say this talks
about the father himself. Does ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda agree that there's
a separate prohibition for the father himself? That's a question of a
קל וחומר kal vachomer from father's brother. Okay, now back to the
רבנן. Rabbanan רבנן, Rabbanan, אזהרה לאשת אביו מנא להו, azhara l'eishet aviv
m'na lehu, where do the רבנן Rabbanan, know the the prohibition of
אשת אביו? Okay, now it's a very strange point. So what? If
this means father himself, אשת אביו is an explicit פסוק pasuk, down
here. So the גמרא says נפקא להו מערות אשת אביך לא תגלה.
nafka lehu m'ervat eishet avicha lo tegaleh. What do you mean? You
don't need you don't need to stick it up here. You got
a whole פסוק pasuk, down here that's about father's wife. לר' יהודה,
L'Reb Yehuda, ההוא מיבעי ליה לאזהרה לאשת אביו לאחר מיתה. hu mibaya
lei l'azhara l'eishet aviv l'achar mita. So ר' יהודה, Reb Yehuda, since
he got אשת אביו up here, okay, this פסוק pasuk here, although
you could say it's אשת אב who's not the mother, but the
other thing this פסוק passuk down here is doing by giving it
a whole separate פסוק passuk is to tell you that this prohibition
remains even after the father is dead, which is a big חידוש.
chiddush. You might think אשת אב is only as long as she's
currently the father's wife. The seeming repetition for ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda
tells you even after the father is dead. ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, now the
רבנן, where do they know that? הוא מסיפא דקרא נפקא. hu m'seifa
d'kra nafka. They get it from the end of the פסוק. passuk
ערבת אביך היא. ervat avicha hi. ערבת אביך ervat avicha here is
superfluous. Why didn't it just say ערבת אשת אביך לא תגלה? ervat
eishet avicha lo tegaleh? These last three words are superfluous. These last
three words extend it to include even after the father's dead. Okay.
ור' יהודה, V'Reb Yehuda, now what does ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda do
with this? Okay, so ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda ההוא מיבעי ליה משום
אשת אב אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום אשת איש. hu mibaya
lei mishum eishet av ata mechayvo v'i ata mechayvo mishum eishet ish.
Ah, now we have something that sort of goes against the משנה,
Mishna, but the same way up here, since it ended with אמך
היא, this is a nice parallel, since it ended with אמך היא
to tell you somebody who's double status, you're only חייב for אמך.
Here since it ends with אשת אביך היא, eishet avicha hi, it
tells you that if she's a double status, she's both father's wife
and currently father's wife, she's a married woman, then then it's only
for the category of father's wife, not for the category of married
woman. So therefore so the גמרא says one minute, we only know
ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda does this double status thing with mother. We
don't know that he does it with with a case of like
father's wife. והתנן, v'hatnan, our משנה Mishna teaches הבא על אשת אב
חייב עליה משום אשת אב ומשום אשת איש, haba al eishet av
chayav aleha mishum eishet av u'mishum eishet ish, that a man who
has intercourse with his father's wife transgresses two, father's wife and married
woman, בין בחיי אביו בין לאחר מיתת אביו, bein b'chayei aviv bein
l'achar mitat aviv, whether the father's alive or dead. ולא פליג ר'
יהודה, v'lo palig Reb Yehuda, ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda doesn't disagree. So
how can you say? I mean it's a nice read of the
פסוק, passuk right? The only liability is mother, the only liability is
father's wife, and other statuses don't matter. It's a great read of
the פסוק, passuk but we never heard ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda say
it. So the
גמרא says אמר אביי פליגי בברייתא. amar Abaye pligi b'braita. Fine, in
the משנה Mishna he doesn't say that he disagrees, but I've got
a ברייתא, braita, although he doesn't tell me the ברייתא, braita, somewhere
in a ברייתא braita ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda says the same idea
here, that the only status you'd be liable for is for the
father's wife and not for a married woman. Okay. ורבנן, now the
רבנן, עונש לאשת אב לאחר מיתה מנא להו? onesh l'eishet av l'achar
mita m'na lehu? Where now that we've got included in here, right,
there's a question, does this mean אשת אב or does this mean
the father ממש? Down here we manage to include the father's wife
after death, okay, after the father dies, okay, question about whether double
status here. So what we don't know now is and we've got
everything included in this פסוק passuk here, the only question is where
do we get the punishment for father's wife after death? Here we
get the prohibition, where do we get the punishment? How do we
know to include that here? Okay. עונש לאשת אב לאחר מיתה מנא
להו, onesh l'eishet av l'achar mita m'na lehu, where do they know
that from? בשלמא לר' יהודה מייתי לה מגזירה שוה. bishlama l'Reb Yehuda
ma'isi lah m'gezeira shava. ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda remember we have this
גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, right? Remember that from earlier? Okay, so once
you've got this גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, you can שלעפ schlep in
pretty much everything we know over here, okay, and say that this
includes this is about אשת אב, down here we know אשת אב
applies לאחר מיתת אביו, achar mitat aviv, so we שלעפ schlep it
all into here for the punishment. אלא רבנן Ela Rabbanan who never
held of a גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, מנא להו? m'na lehu? Where
do they know the punishment for
אשת אב לאחר מיתה? eishet av l'achar mita? אמר לך ההוא ערבת
אביו גילה. amar lach hahu ervat aviv gila. What are they going
to do with this extra phrase? So מחזקי להו *machaziki lehu* לעונש
אשת אביו לאחר מיתה *l'onesh aishess aviv l'achar misa*. They're going to
say this includes father's wife after death, after the father dies. They're
not going to use his גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, they're going to
do that. Okay, now we've got a problem though because just to
see if anybody's paying attention, this is such an easy גמרא *Gemara*,
I'm sure you're all totally on top of it. Okay, so what
did רבי יהודה *Reb Yehuda* fundamentally use this ערות אביו גילה *ervas
aviv gilah*, the גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* to do? To bring what
case into? Mother, right? It's right on the board, you don't even
have to remember it. So if the רבנן *Rabbanan* don't hold of
the גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and they use this for father's wife
after death, where are the רבנן *Rabbanan* going to get the עונש
*onesh* for mother who's not a father's wife? Okay, so that's what
the גמרא *Gemara* ends with. ורבנן עונש לאמו שאינה אשת אביו מנא
להו *Verabbanan onesh l'imo she-eina aishess aviv minalohu*? Where would they get
this from? אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר קרא *Amar Rav
Sheshes brei d'Rav Idi amar kra*, the verse says אמך היא *imcha
hi*. We're back to the אמך היא *imcha hi* because right, we
never figured out what the רבנן *Rabbanan* do with אמך היא *imcha
hi*. אמך היא *Imcha hi* for רבי יהודה *Reb Yehuda* says only
one status, not both statuses. But אמך היא *imcha hi*, here's what
the רבנן *Rabbanan* are going to do with it. עשאו הכתוב לאמו
שאינה אשת אביו כאמו שהיא אשת אביו *Asao haksav l'imo she-eina aishess
aviv k'imo she-hi aishess aviv*. So this says all sort of mothers
are the same. A mother who's a father's wife and a mother
who's not a father's wife have all the same הלכות *halachos*. Okay,
and since here included in father's wife is also a mother who's
a father's wife, right? So this includes mother who's a father's wife,
and this tells us אמך היא *imcha hi*, so anything that's true
about a mother who's a father's wife is also true about just
a plain mother. And therefore since this punishment applies for a mother
who's a father's wife, אמך היא *imcha hi* tells us it also
applies to just a plain mother. So we've figured out perfectly how
all the extra phrases are used, and everybody agrees pretty much in
everything except for the debate of if it's a double status do
you get only for mother or do you get even for father's
wife? And maybe this question about whether there's a prohibition of intercourse
with the father himself. What did they do before they had whiteboards?
That's what I want to know. I'm thinking I did not know
how you can read this גמרא *Gemara* without like putting something up
on the board and looking at it. I mean it's hard enough
even then. Okay.
לוחות *Luchos*? Clay tablets, right? I know, I don't mean the technology,
I meant I don't think they always teach with visual aids. Okay.
Anyway.
It was all oral.
I know.
Imagine if you had people acting out. You have this person, this
person...
if you can keep all the פסוקים pessukim *psukim* in your mind,
if you have a good like just visual memory like, you know,
can imagine this stuff visually you can move the pieces around. Anyway,
fine. Now we switch gears to the next one, as I said,
this is of course, you know, very challenging given the sort of
sensibilities that we have today and but we're just going to read
this and explain this on its own terms. Okay. הבא על הזכור
ועל הבהמה *Haba al hazachur v'al habeheimah*, a man who has intercourse
with a male. Did I skip? Oh, I skipped the last two
lines. הבא על כלתו *Haba al kalaso*. So now we get the
case about daughter-in-law. וחייב נמי משום אשת בנו *v'chayav nami mishum aishess
bno*. So the גמרא *Gemara* thinks that the פסוק passuk *pasuk* is
talking about two prohibitions, the פסוק passuk *pasuk* says ערות כלתך לא
תגלה אשת בנך היא לא תגלה ערותה *ervas kallascha lo segaleh aishess
bincha hi lo segaleh ervasah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* thinks that maybe
there are two identities, one called כלה *kallah*, daughter-in-law, and the other
called your son's wife. So of course like so it seems like
maybe it's just a double status to every case of a daughter-in-law.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says וחייב נמי משום אשת בנו *v'chayav nami
mishum aishess bno*. אמר אביי Abaye פתח הכתוב בכלתו וסיים באשת בנו
לומר לך זו היא כלתו זו היא אשת בנו *Amar Abaye pasach
haksav b'kalaso v'siyem b'aishess bno lomar lach zo hi kalaso zo hi
aishess bno*. No, the פסוק passuk *pasuk* isn't saying that there's two
identities here. What כלתו *kalaso* means is son's wife. It means daughter-in-law.
They're not two statuses, it's all the same prohibition.
But if they're divorced?
So that's אשת בנו לאחר מיתה *aishess bno l'achar misa* and yeah,
and the משנה *Mishna* says that you also are liable, that's explicit
in the משנה *Mishna*. הבא על כלתו בין לאחר מיתה בין מן
האירוסין בין מן הנישואין *haba al kalaso bein l'achar misa bein min
ha'erusin bein min hanisuin*. Now the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't tell us how
we know that from, right? It's not going through all the דרשות
*drashos* for all of the things, which I would say thank God.
Okay, but anyway. All right. Moving on. הבא על הזכור ועל הבהמה
*Haba al hazachur v'al habeheimah*, a man who has intercourse with a
male. Now it's interesting the phrase זכור zachur. *zachur* as opposed to
זכר zachar *zachar*. רש״י *Rashi* says זכור zachur *zachur*... I don't know
where רש״י *Rashi* knows this from, but רש״י *Rashi* says זכור *zachur*
specifically refers when we're talking about the man who is being penetrated.
So so that's sort of the way of referring to it. It's
anal sex from the perspective of the man being penetrated.
Passive?
Passive of the verb.
Yeah, no I know הבא *haba*, why זכור *zachur* not זכר zachar
*zachar*?
No, זכור *zachur* would be like סגור *sagur* or שמור *shamur*.
Oh, he has... he has been maled? Oh, interesting.
Interesting, interesting. Anyway, רש״י *Rashi* says that's what it's describing. Okay, so
when it talks about
the actor, the penetrator, it refers to זכר zachar, *zachar*, not זכור
*zachur*. Okay. הבא על זכור ועל בהמה behemah. or on intercourse with
an animal, זה האיש המביא את הבהמה עליו zeh ha-ish ha-mevi et
ha-behemah alav and a woman who sort of has intercourse with an
animal, brings a male animal upon her, בסקילה. bi-skilah. All of those
are with stoning.
אם אדם חטא בהמה מה חטא? Im adam chata behemah mah chata?
Now fine, the man sinned, why was it the animal's fault? Why
are you stoning the animal? אלא לפי שבאה לאדם תקלה על ידה,
Ela lefi she-ba'ah le-adam takalah al yadah, because it caused a person
to stumble, so therefore it has to also be killed. וסיפא דקרא
כתיב תסקלו. Ve-seifa de-kra ketiv tiskalu. Therefore it says that you should
stone it. This is somehow seen as it's not to blame, but
it was the, even you know, it's somehow it's seen as a
bad thing and therefore we have to get rid of it. דבר
אחר, Davar acher, שלא תהא בהמה עוברת בשוק ויאמרו זו היא שנסקל
פלוני על ידה. she-lo te-he behemah overet ba-shuk ve-yomru zo hi she-niskal
ploni al yadah. Or maybe it's not somehow some identifying of the
object or the thing even though it didn't have a will or
whatever as a bad or as evil, that's the first thing. No,
it caused evil even though it's not evil in itself, something that
caused evil we have to destroy it. The second approach is that
no, it's that it just makes people remember the sin. It's not
about this thing somehow being associated, somehow metaphysically being bad and having
to be destroyed, it's that it causes people to remember the human
sin and what happened to the human being, and so there are
cases you might imagine where you have one of those categories and
not the other. Anyway we'll see about that in the Gemara, but
those obviously point in different directions. Okay, let's take a look at
the Gemara. זכר מנלן? Zachar minalan? What's the source about male, about
the man? דתנו רבנן: de-tanu rabbanan: איש, ish, okay, a man. פרט
לקטן. prat le-katan. אשר ישכב את זכר משכבי אשה תועבה
היא.
Asher yishkav et zachar mishkevei
ishah
toevah hi.
Okay, the pasuk is זכר, zachar I understand in the rabbinic language
it's זכור. Okay, it says איש אשר ישכב את זכר משכבי אשה
תועבה היא. Ish asher yishkav et zachar mishkevei ishah toevah hi. Okay,
איש פרט לקטן. ish prat le-katan. אשר ישכב, asher yishkav so it's
only talking about not a minor. אשר ישכב that sleeps, את זכר,
et zachar, בין גדול בין קטן. bein gadol bein katan. So it
says a male, it doesn't say with a man, so means whether
the one being penetrated whether it's an adult or a minor it
still transgresses. This is always the question, look in general we'll see
some interesting debate right, but in general you don't need by these
prohibitions of intercourse you don't need both parties to be adults, but
you need it to be defined, obviously if nobody's an adult nobody's
going to get punished, so at least one of them has to
be an adult to get punished, but they don't both have to
be and you but you need a certain minimum age for it
to be defined as an act of intercourse. So the rabbis say
that the minimum age for a girl is three and the minimum
age for a boy is nine. Okay, where we learn that from
whatever we'll worry about that later. Okay, so therefore we're
saying that the man being penetrated doesn't have to be an adult,
but he would have to be a minimum age and there's going
to be an interesting discussion in the Gemara what would that minimum
age be for the man being penetrated. If the man being penetrated
is the adult then the man doing the penetrating would have to
if could even be a minor okay but it would have to
be nine years old. Alright, so you got the basic parameters here?
Okay, fine.
So the one being penetrated is not being stoned, just the one
doing the?
If he's a minor he's not.
But if he's an adult they both? They would both do, did
you already say before that when it said
the word זכר it meant the one being penetrated?
Right. So is he the only one being stoned?
No, they're both, both. Okay, but the question is that like here
it's saying that the one being penetrated can doesn't have to be
an adult, but in a way it's actually true in the reverse
as well which is if the one being penetrated is an adult
he would be liable if the one penetrating is a minor as
long as he's nine years old. Okay, but they don't both have
to be adults. בין גדול בין קטן, bein gadol bein katan, אשר
ישכב את זכר asher yishkav et zachar בין גדול בין קטן. bein
gadol bein katan. משכבי אשה, mishkevei ishah, the sleepings of a woman.
So what does this mean? מגלה לך הכתוב ששם משכבות אשה. megaleh
lach ha-katuv she-shem mishkevot ishah. So since by the men we're talking
about anal intercourse, okay, but it says the sleepings in the plural,
you know, the lyings with a woman I guess I should say
for lyings with a woman. So the double, the plural is used
to tell me a general principle by forbidden sexual relations that intercourse
is defined whether it's vaginal or it's anal intercourse when dealing with
a woman. So you learn it both from the plural of משכבי,
mishkevei, there are two types of intercourse with a woman and also
from the fact that in this case we're talking about anal intercourse.
So this teaches you the general principle that intercourse is defined as
either vaginal or anal intercourse. Okay, I guess it's now the time
to say I mean whatever it's always relevant but now's the time
to say that intercourse is also only defined by in הלכה halacha
by penetration with the penis. So that's why for example women, you
know, two women having sex is never really recognized in הלכה, halacha,
you know, as an act of sex, which is why there's a
question of even what status to give
it. An act of sex is defined as a penis penetrating an
orifice and it's basically you know either vaginal or anal so in
the case of two men it would be anal. Okay so now
it says like this not oral though vaginal or anal. Okay. אמר
רבי ישמעאל Amar Rabbi Yishmael הרי זה בא ללמד ונמצא למד. harei
zeh ba lelamed venimtsa lamed. This is coming to teach and it
comes up you know it's the פסוק passuk is coming to teach
you about a man what constitutes this actual forbidden act of intercourse
but you wind up learning from this to other cases you wind
up learning in general what's defined as intercourse. Okay. מות יומתו mot
yumatu they shall be put to death בסקילה beskila אתה אומר בסקילה
או אינו אלא באחת מכל מיתות האמורות בתורה atah omer beskila o
eino ela be'achat mikol mitot ha'amurot baTorah נאמר כאן דמיהם בם ונאמר
באוב וידעוני דמיהם בם ne'emar kan dmeihem bam vene'emar be'ov veyidoni dmeihem
bam מה להלן בסקילה אף כאן בסקילה mah lehalan beskila af kan
beskila fine. העונש שמענו Onesh shamanu so that's the פסוק passuk in
קדושים Kedoshim okay מות יומתו שניהם דמיהם בם mot yumatu shneihem dmeihem
bam okay now אזהרה מניין azhara minayin where's the prohibition going back
to אחרי מות Acharei Mot תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ואת זכר לא
תשכב משכבי אשה תועבה היא ve'et zachar lo tishkav mishkevei isha to'evah
hi I think I accidentally was ending the פסוק pasuk. before that
way okay the פסוק pasuk we just read was the פסוק pasuk,
that ended with מות יומתו שניהם דמיהם בם mot yumatu shneihem dmeihem
bam the פסוק pasuk in אחרי מות Acharei Mot is ואת זכר
לא תשכב משכבי אשה תועבה היא ve'et zachar lo tishkav mishkevei isha
to'evah hi okay so that's the negative prohibition למדנו אזהרה לשוכב lamadnu
azhara lashochev now that's לא תשכב lo tishkav the one who sleeps
meaning the one who does who penetrates אזהרה לנשכב מניין azhara lanishkav
minayin how about the the one who's penetrated תלמוד לומר לא יהיה
קדש מבני ישראל Talmud lomar lo yihyeh kadesh mivnei yisrael. so this
is very interesting one פסוק pasuk goes to it a completely different
place to learn this out from a verse that says you shall
have no male prostitute. Now what is the definition of a male
prostitute? So very often you could say maybe a male prostitute hired
by a woman but often male prostitutes the standard would be hired
by men for you know for sex between two men and very
often when male prostitutes are hired for that purpose they are the
one who are they're it's for their being penetrated not the one
doing the penetration. So therefore it actually is a very reasonable read
of that פסוק okay that that is to coming to now you
might say that's only in the context of prostitution okay we're extending
it to to the act in general okay but to sort of
think that that's the type of act that this פסוק is referring
to is a very reasonable read.
Yes that verse in דברים Devarim separately prohibits a קדש kadesh and
a קדשה. kadesha.
Right so clearly it's a male prostitute right distinct from female. Okay
ואומר ve'omer now how do we know I just sort of gave
you a sociological explanation of why it makes sense to think that
that's what it's talking about but the גמרא is going to give
a explanation based on the verse. ואומר ve'omer and the verse says
וגם קדש היה בארץ
עשו ככל תועבות הגוים אשר הוריש vegam kadesh hayah va'arets asu kechol
to'avot hagoyim asher horish etc. There was it's talking about all the
evil that was done in the time of רחבעם Rechavam and it
says there were even male prostitutes they did like all the abominations
of the nation. So the keyword here is תועבה to'evah okay and
it says תועבה to'evah by by sex between by intercourse between two
men okay so therefore since this says that a קדש kadesh is
associated with a form of forbidden sex that's identified as תועבה to'evah
we can sort of figure out that we're talking here about sex
between two men and therefore we can learn that the prohibition of
a קדש kadesh prohibits that. Okay דברי רבי ישמעאל divrei Rabbi Yishmael
that's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva
omer רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says אינו צריך eino tsarich you don't
need that verse הרי הוא אומר harei hu omer ואת זכר לא
תשכב משכבי אשה ve'et zachar lo tishkav mishkevei isha don't sleep the
lain with a woman קרי ביה karei beh לא תשכב lo tishakhev
shall not be slept with. So not surprisingly רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
learns it from like a tiny little micro read of a פסוק
you know playing with a word a certain way and רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael goes to a פסוק that seems to me more directly
addressing the issue. Okay so that's.
Sorry רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva reads it
לא תשכב lo tishakhev passively and actively. Both ways. Both ways. Right
both ways. קרי ביה karei beh means you also read it the
following way. Now he doesn't tell us what allows him to to
have that additional read you know might be a point like well
since there are no vowels in the פסוקים we are entitled to
read it multiple ways you know normally you want there to be
something little extra signaling it. Okay now בהמה מנלן behema menalan now
how do you know that the act of intercourse with an animal's
forbidden דתנו רבנן detanu rabanan איש ish פרט לקטן perat lekatan okay
a man excluding a minor אשר יתן שכבתו בבהמה asher yiten shichavto
bivehema that gives his lying with with an animal בין גדולה בין
קטנה bein gedola bein ktana whether the animal is an adult or
a minor doesn't matter about the animal okay מות יומת mot yumat
shall be put to death בסקילה beskila אתה אומר בסקילה או אינו
אלא באחת מכל מיתות האמורות בתורה atah omer beskila o eino ela
be'achat mikol mitot ha'amurot baTorah you say stoning but maybe it's all
any of the the other executions נאמר כאן תהרגו ונאמר להלן כי
הרג תהרגנו ne'emar kan taharogu vene'emar lehalan ki harog tahargenu you shall
kill them and it says by הרוג תהרגנו harog tahargenu רש"י Rashi
tells me let me see one minute 13:10.
ידך תהיה בו
בראשונה להמיתו ויד כל העם באחרונה ובערת הרע מקרבך.
Yadecha tihyeh bo
barishonah lahamito
veyad kol
ha'am ba'acharonah uvi'arta hara mikirbecha.
Now we only have to know what is it talking about? דברים
Devarim 13:10 or 11 maybe.
Let's take a look.
Oh, המדיח. Hamesis. Okay, the person who seduces somebody to commit idolatry.
Okay, כי הרג תהרגנו. Ki harog targenu. מה
להלן בסקילה אף כאן בסקילה. Mah lehalan biskilah, af kan biskilah. There
סקילה, skilah. which we'll find out, so therefore here too בסקילה. biskilah.
Fine, למדנו עונש. Lamanu onesh. Now that's the punishment. By the way,
the reason all of these things are starting with the punishment and
working back to the prohibition, you might think that's the reverse order,
but that's because that's our פרק. perek. Our פרק perek is to
tell you here are the people that get the following execution of
סקילה. skilah. So the discussion starts with show me that they get
סקילה. skilah. Fine, you've shown me that they get סקילה. skilah, Now
let's understand the prohibition. Tell me where is it that the verse
is prohibiting
it. למדנו עונש לשוכב. Lamanu onesh leshochev. Okay, למדנו עונש לשוכב. Lamanu
onesh leshochev. לנשכב מנין? Lanishkav minayin? How do you know about the
man who is penetrated by an animal? Now, a woman penetrated by
an animal is an explicit verse. ואשה לא תעמד לפני בהמה לרבעה
תבל הוא, Ve'ishah lo ta'amod lifne behemah leriv'ah tevel hu, I think
that's the פסוק. Okay, but how do you know a man who
allows himself to be penetrated, brings an animal on him to be
penetrated? How do you know that's prohibited? תלמוד לומר כל שכב עם
בהמה מות יומת Talmud lomar kol shochev im behemah mot yumat is
an extra פסוק that prohibits an act of bestiality. אם אינו ענין
לשוכב, Im eino inyan leshochev, if you don't need it to prohibit
the man doing the penetrating, cause that we know from another פסוק,
תניהו ענין לנשכב, teneyhu inyan lanishkav, so we can also apply it
to the case of the man being penetrated. Okay, למדנו עונש. Lamanu
onesh. So that's the prohibition. Now, it's what I was saying before.
Now that we're done, I mean that's the punishment. Now that we're
done with the punishment, which is our primary focus, let's go back,
now we know that they get סקילה, let's go back and show
where the prohibition is. למדנו עונש בין לשוכב בין לנשכב. Lamanu onesh
bein leshochev bein lanishkav. אזהרה מנין? Azharah minayin? Where is it prohibited?
תלמוד לומר ובכל בהמה לא תתן שכבתך לטמאה בה. Talmud lomar uvechol
behemah lo titten shechovtecha le'tom'ah bah. In any animal you should not
give your lying to be defiled by it. למדנו אזהרה לשוכב, Lamanu
azharah leshochev, fine, that's the penetrator. לנשכב מנין? Lanishkav minayin? Being penetrated
where do you know it? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar לא יהיה קדש
מבני ישראל. lo yihyeh kadesh mi-bnei Yisrael Back to רבי ישמעאל. Rebbi
Yishmael. Okay, so he's gonna include in this not only the case
of the man being penetrated by a man, but a man being
penetrated by an animal. Obviously, that's a very difficult
juxtaposition. What? ואומר וגם קדש היה בארץ Ve'omer vegam kadesh hayah va'aretz
etc. So since it links קדש kadesh with forbidden sexuality that is
labeled as תועבה, to'evah, it's going to extend it not only to
the case of the man, but also the case of the בהמה.
behemah. Now the problem is that it never says תועבה to'evah by
the בהמה. behemah So we're going to see later, it says a
general תועבה to'evah by all the forbidden acts of sex. So we're
going to see later that אביי Abaye is going to be saying
that רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael didn't really mean this. Okay, that it
doesn't say תועבה to'evah by a בהמה behemah. and this פסוק is
only about the case of the two men and actually it's not
serious, it's not what this means. Okay, but for now somehow we
are linking this to include even this case of the לנשכב nishkav
by the בהמה. behemah.
What do you mean to change?
אביי Abaye with רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael because it doesn't say תועבה
to'evah and I think because maybe he's just bothered that those are
two completely separate types of things, you know, thinking about sex between
two people
even if it's the prohibition, even if it's two men, and sex
between a human person and an animal. Okay, דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei
Rebbi Yishmael. That's what רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר
אינו צריך, Rebbi Akiva omer eino tzarich, הרי הוא אומר לא תתן
שכבתך לא תתן שכיבתך. harei hu omer lo titten shechovtecha, lo titten
shechivatecha.
Again, both ways. Don't put your lying and your being laid with.
Okay, now. Now that we have this debate, we're gonna have now
a little fun, haha, to speak about like if you do multiple
things, since some of these verses overlap, right? For רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi
Yishmael, קדש kadesh includes two types of things: the נשכב nishkav for
the man and the נשכב nishkav, for the בהמה. behema For רבי
יהודה, the same פסוק that prohibits the penetrating prohibits the being penetrated.
So there are ways in which if a person does multiple things,
you don't get, they're not multiple prohibitions because some of them overlap
from the same verse. So let's take a
look. Okay,
הבא על זכור והביא עליו זכור. Haba al zachur vehevi alav zachur.
So here רש"י Rashi points out, right? The first is זכור and
the second is זכר because one is the penetrated and the other
is the penetrator. Okay, so a man who does these two acts,
both penetrates and is penetrated, and he does it in like, you
know, one state of forgetfulness. So the question is how many קרבנות
korbanot does he bring? And the number of קרבנות korbanot you bring
is how many if a man does the same prohibition multiple times
in one state of forgetfulness, okay, let's say somebody makes five fires
on שבת Shabbos but they in one state of forgetfulness, they only
bring one חטאת. chatas. Okay, so if it's the same sin multiple
times, it's only one sin offering. If it's different sins, then it's
different sin offerings. So this gives us an opportunity to explore are
these different sins or the same ones? How many sin offerings does
he bring? sin offerings. So if in one state of forgetfulness, doesn't
have to mean at the exact same moment, a man both does
the act of penetrating and is penetrated, אמר רבי אבהו *Amar Rabbi
Avahu*, לדברי רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael חייב שתים *lidivre Rabbi Yishmael chayav
shtayim*, for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rabbi Yishmael* that's two sacrifices, one
for the את זכר לא תשכב משכבי אשה *et zachar lo tishkav
mishkeve ishah* and the other for לא יהיה קדש lo yihye kadesh,
*lo yiheyeh kadesh*, completely separate prohibitions. Okay, חדא מלא תשכב וחדא מלא
יהיה קדש kadesh. *chada milo tishkav vechada milo yiheyeh kadesh*. ורבי עקיבא
אינו חייב אלא אחת *veRabbi Akiva eino chayav ela achat*. It's the
same prohibition. לא תשכב ולא תשכב *lo tishkav velo tishachev*—חדא היא *chada
hi*. It's a play on the words לא תשכב *lo tishkav* but
essentially it's the same prohibition. He's just saying there's no difference which
side you're doing. But it's basically the same prohibition. So therefore it
would be the same act done twice or the same prohibition done
twice and only
one קרבן *korban*. Similarly, הבא על הבהמה והביא בהמה עליו haba al
habehema vehevi behema alav. *haba al habeheimah veheivi beheimah alav*, okay, a
man penetrates an animal and is penetrated by an animal. אמר רבי
אבהו *Amar Rabbi Avahu*, לדברי רבי ישמעאל חייב שתים *lidivre Rabbi Yishmael
chayav shtayim*. For רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* it's two prohibitions and two
sacrifices. חדא מלא תתן שכבתך *chada milo titein shichavtecha* וחדא מלא יהיה
קדש kadesh *vechada milo yiheyeh kadesh*. Okay, one for the act with
the animal and the other לא יהיה קדש lo yihye kadesh, *lo
yiheyeh kadesh*. ולדברי רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אינו חייב אלא אחת *ulidivre
Rabbi Akiva eino chayav ela achat*. It's one prohibition. שכבתך שכיבתך חדא
היא *shichavtecha shichivtecha chada hi*. What he's basically saying is the way
he reads the פסוק *pasuk*, it doesn't matter which side of the
act you're taking. It's all the same prohibition. So therefore it's only
going to be one קרבן *korban*. אביי אמר *Abaye amar*, now here
comes אביי *Abaye* to do the pushback I told you about, אפילו
לדברי רבי ישמעאל נמי אינו חייב אלא אחת *afilu lidivre Rabbi Yishmael
nami eino chayav ela achat*. No, רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* doesn't really
mean it when he says the case of קדש kadesh, *kadesh* is
a separate thing, includes the case of an animal. דכי כתיב לא
יהיה קדש kadesh בגברי כתיב *dechi ketiv lo yiheyeh kadesh begavre ketiv*.
It's talking about people, it's not talking about animals. And the way,
again, תוספות *Tosafot* explains it, it's because it doesn't say תועבה *toevah*
by the case of the animals anyway. אלא לרבי ישמעאל אזהרה לנשכב
מנלן *ela leRabbi Yishmael azharah lenishkav minalan*? Okay, so now given that,
where does רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* learn the prohibition of נשכב *nishkav*
for the case of בהמה behema *beheimah*? נפקא ליה מכל שוכב עם
בהמה behema, מות יומת *nafka lei mikol shovev im beheimah mot yumet*,
the extra פסוק *pasuk*. אם אינו עניין לשוכב תנהו עניין לנשכב *im
eino inyan leshochev tenehu inyan lenishkav*. So before we did that to
say the punishment, but here we're going to double use it also
to say the prohibition. Since it's an extra פסוק *pasuk*, it'll apply
also to the one who is penetrated by an animal. And now
because רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* now effectively agrees to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, it's not some separate category of קדש *kadesh*. By
the case of the animal, it's all learned out from the פסוק
*pasuk* of the same פסוק *pasuk* of sleeping with an animal. So
since it's all learned out from the same פסוק *pasuk*, it's all
one prohibition, and therefore he would agree that in this case it's
only one קרבן *korban*. ואפקיה רחמנא לנשכב בלשון שוכב *veafkeih rachmana lenishkav
belashon shochev*. It uses the word to tell מה שוכב עונש והזהיר
*mah shochev onesh vehizhir*. Now the problem is of course that this
פסוק *pasuk* of שוכב עם בהמה behema *shochev im beheimah* is only
about the punishment. But now
it's going to say the following: okay, but once we're saying it
refers to the נשכב *nishkav*, so now we're going to make a
link. The same way by the case of the שוכב *shochev*, if
it both has a punishment and a prohibition, אף נשכב *af nishkav*,
this פסוק *pasuk* of שוכב עם בהמה *shochev im beheimah* which we're
saying is talking about the נשכב *nishkav*, although the פסוק
*pasuk* is only about the punishment, but because of the link עונש
והזהיר *onesh vehizhir*, we infer also the prohibition. But bottom line is
we're saying according to אביי *Abaye*, the same way רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* learns out לא תתן שכבתך שכיבתך *lo titein shichavtecha shichivtecha*, רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* also says that the prohibition of both sides of
the issue of the בהמה *beheimah* is learned from the פסוקים *pesukim*
of כל שוכב עם בהמה kol shochev im behema *kol shochev im
beheimah* and it's all one prohibition. Okay, so for אביי *Abaye* in
this case, everybody would agree there's only one קרבן *korban*. Let's read
one more of these cases, get through because these are just all
of a set, okay. הנרבע לזכר והנרבע לבהמה *hanirba lezachar vehanirba lebeheimah*.
So somebody both is penetrated by a male and by an animal,
again,
separate times but in one state of forgetfulness.
אמר רבי אבהו *Amar Rabbi Avahu*, לדברי רבי עקיבא חייב שתים *lidivre
Rabbi Akiva chayav shtayim*. For רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that's obviously two
separate prohibitions, right? One is כל שוכב *kol shochev*, whatever, לא תתן
שכבתך *lo titein shichavtecha*, whatever, לא תשכב *lo tishkav*. חדא מלא תשכב
את זכר *chada milo tishkav et zachar* which is לא תשכב *lo
tishachev* וחדא מלא תתן שכבתך *vechada milo titein shichavtecha* which is שכיבתך
*shichivtecha*. But two totally separate prohibitions. לדברי רבי ישמעאל אינו חייב אלא
אחת *lidivre Rabbi Yishmael eino chayav ela achat*. אידי ואידי לא יהיה
קדש הוא *idei ve'idei lo yiheyeh kadesh hu*. For רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi
Yishmael* it's all the same prohibition of לא יהיה קדש *lo yiheyeh
kadesh*. Okay. Obviously there's something here, again, as I said, you could
think about that's challenging or whatever, disturbing about thinking about anybody who
is playing the being-penetrated role being thought of—look, this is the way
it was in Roman society too, you know, that the act of
penetration was also an act of power and they would use like
boys or slaves or whatever to be the ones that were penetrated.
And not just women. Well, in Roman society. What, women, well, you
mean but how is that different than just normal intercourse? What do
you mean? You mean anal? Well, it's the same kind of intercourse
but men would take other men's wives. Oh, as acts of power
you're saying. Oh, I see, interesting. Anyway, so anyway, so it's interesting
his link with קדש *kadesh* and also the link with בהמה *beheimah*,
I mean obviously it's disturbing but interesting. Okay, so anyway, אביי אמר
*Abaye amar*, אפילו לדברי רבי ישמעאל נמי חייב שתים *afilu lidivre Rabbi
Yishmael nami chayav shtayim*. Nope, even רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* would say
two, because remember אביי *Abaye* rejects putting the בהמה *beheimah* in the
קדש *kadesh* category. דכתיב כל שוכב עם בהמה מות יומת *dechitiv kol
shochev im beheimah mot yumet*, אם אינו עניין לשוכב תנהו עניין לנשכב
*im eino inyan leshochev tenehu inyan lenishkav*. ואפקיה רחמנא לנשכב בלשון שוכב
*veafkeih rachmana lenishkav belashon shochev*, מה שוכב עונש והזהיר *mah shochev onesh
vehizhir*. ענש והזהיר אף נשכב ענש והזהיר. Fine, this is basically saying
רבי ישמעאל also gets the case of being penetrated by an animal
from כל שוכב עם בהמה and he doesn't include it in קדש.
They're not both in the קדש category. אבל, Aval, last one, הבא
על הזכר והביא זכר עליו, haba al hazachar vehevi zachar alav, הבא
על הבהמה והביא בהמה עליו. Somebody did all four things in one
state of forgetfulness, okay?
בין לרבי אבהו בין לאביי, bein lerabbi avahu bein leabaye, whichever way
you read the רבי ישמעאל, לרבי ישמעאל חייב שלוש. lerabbi yishmael chayav
shalosh. It's three. What are the three? So you have the לא
יהיה קדש, which covers the two cases of the נשכב, and then
you have ואת זכר לא תשכב ve'et zachar lo tishkav and ובכל
בהמה לא תתן שכבתך. uvechol behema lo titten shechovtecha. So those are
the three. Even for אביי that says בהמה isn't in the קדש,
but בהמה is in the
ובכל בהמה לא תתן שכבתך. uvechol behema lo titten shechovtecha. So you
get, you know, you get the זכר, בהמה, and the קדש that
covers all the four so those three cover all
four. לרבי עקיבא חייב שתיים. lerabbi akiva chayav shtayim. רבי עקיבא is
two because רבי עקיבא only has, doesn't have לא יהיה קדש, right?
The case about the זכר is both sides and the case about
the male about the בהמה is both sides. So therefore somebody does
all those four things, it's only the two prohibitions each one done
twice. Okay, that is the end of that. Okay, we will continue
with this. We are now caught up and we will continue with
this.